<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rss.xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Hake Hardware Blog</title>
        <link>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>Hake Hardware Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New Format]]></title>
            <link>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format</link>
            <guid>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Getting Familiar]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-familiar">Getting Familiar<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format#getting-familiar" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting Familiar" title="Direct link to Getting Familiar">​</a></h2>
<p>If you are here you have probably noticed I am now using a wiki-style layout for my guides.</p>
<p>I wanted to replicate some of the content really quick to better understand how Docusaurus (the platform that runs this thing) works and get familiar with it. Now that I have had a week or so to play around I'm getting the feel of things and starting to find some direction.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-format">New Format<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format#new-format" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Format" title="Direct link to New Format">​</a></h2>
<p>My plan is to have a Wiki section and an Articles section. We are currently in the Articles section. This is where I will create more long-form style content. Maybe a review, or unboxing, or test of something where I want to share the results. It will be a place where I do not feel bad rambling on about things. In the Wiki section, I want it to be mostly straight to the point no BS. If you want to set up an Autonomys cluster, you can go to the Wiki and see all the commands and templates I use when creating mine. That point actually brings me to another important point, the Wiki section is for the way I do things. It may not be the official way, and it may not be the best way, but it is how I have made it work. SO, to recap, there will be <strong>Wikis</strong> which is where I will post straight forward guides on how to do all sorts of things and <strong>Articles</strong>, which is where I will post long form content.</p>
<p>As for how my YouTube videos fit in, I imagine every Article will get a YouTube video, and most Wikis will get a YouTube video. The problem with making YouTube videos for the Wikis is that the Wikis will change over time. They are a living document. So the YouTube video will become out dated pretty quickly. However, when that happens it will almost surely be time for a new Article on all the changes, which will have a YouTube video. So it sort of works itself out. To highlight something that I think is really cool - I will do my best to keep the Wiki updated. So you can keep coming back to the same Wiki to get information and it <em>should</em> be updated.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-next">What's Next<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format#whats-next" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's Next" title="Direct link to What's Next">​</a></h2>
<p>Right now I am prepping for Autonomys mainnet. I also have this fun idea to help support my YouTube channel and Wiki, which is to sell COMETs for Autonomys. I have no idea if anyone will buy one, but they are super cool and I will put out some content just on these. And lastly, I want to move a lot of my content over from substack, as well as update some of my older guides. This is a big project as I have been making guides and videos for a year now. But I do not like having things split between substack and Github. I also have some big life changes coming up (baby!) so that will, without a doubt, make things interesting!</p>
<p>For those that read through this whole thing, thank you! Your interactions, whether that is a comment on my videos, likes, subscribing, it is all sincerly appreciated.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-channels">My Channels<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/new_format#my-channels" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My Channels" title="Direct link to My Channels">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@hakehardware" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">YouTube Channel</a></li>
<li><a href="https://discord.gg/uAdsVBWYfX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord Channel</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello COMET]]></title>
            <link>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/hello-comet</link>
            <guid>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/hello-comet</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This article is a work in progress.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>This article is a work in progress.</p></div></div>
<p>It's been about a month since I started testing this tiny Autonomys Farmer capable of 16TB, and I'm honestly impressed.</p>
<p>I wanted to write an article on what the COMET is and why I have a whole section dedicated to them. In short, the COMET consists of a Custom 3D Printed Case + CM3588 (8G/64G) + NAS Kit (4x M.2 NVME, 2.5G NIC) + 60W PSU + Debian OS. The CM3588 gets some noteriety as it was featured by Linus Tech Tips in their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QsM6b5yix0U" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paying for Cloud Storage is Stupid</a> video. Of course it can be used for a NAS, but my use case is focused on Crypto. Specifically, I plan to use 8 of these to farm on the <a href="https://www.autonomys.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Autonomys Network</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="testing-on-autonomys">Testing on Autonomys<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/hello-comet#testing-on-autonomys" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Testing on Autonomys" title="Direct link to Testing on Autonomys">​</a></h2>
<p>Regardless of what you think about Crypto, jamming 4x NVME into such a small form factor is pretty darn cool. Maxing it out with 4x NVME results each NVME running @ PCIe 3.0 x1. This is not a significant amount of bandwidth. However, Autonomys is random read IOPS heavy, not bandwidth heavy. In my testing with 4x 4TB NVMEs fully plotted, I did not have a single missed reward in my week long testing. This can vary based on a lot of factors, but I think it's safe to say PCIe 3.0 x1 will not be an issue at 16TB.</p>
<p>The 2.5G ethernet port allows for very quick plotting over your network, which is perfect for a dedicated Farmer like the COMET. I was not able to saturate the connection with 2x RTX 4090. However, it did appear that the cards were not being fully utilized. For most people, who will be plotting via a single GPU, this would be more than sufficient.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="thermals">Thermals<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/hello-comet#thermals" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Thermals" title="Direct link to Thermals">​</a></h3>
<p>With so much packed into such a tight space, thermals were a bit of a worry. The board comes without any active cooling (however the COMET does have a 5v 50mm dual ball bearing fan). The NVME slots are also VERY tight, so most NVME heatsinks do not fit. I was able to use the ones that are held on by rubberbands. While not pretty, they did over some improvements in use with the COMET as the vents of the case direct air over the NVMEs and CPU.</p>
<p>I recorded some data for both the CPU and the NVMEs as those were the biggest worry. The fan and heatsinks add quite a bit of effort as the 50mm fan requires soldering on the right connector and drilling out the holes for the screws I wanted to use, so I really wanted to see if all of that was worth it. It also adds about $15 in material costs per COMET.</p>
<p>In the below charts, this was done with only the Farmer running, and plotting at about 1 sector per minute. At the time of the tests I was having issues with GPU plotting which is why it was a bit slow. Each test ran for one hour.</p>
<p><strong>No Active Cooling, no NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>No Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p>To really stress things I turned on CPU plotting for the COMET.</p>
<p><strong>No Active Cooling, no NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>No Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<p><strong>Active Cooling, NVME Heatsinks</strong></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="resource-usage">Resource Usage<a href="https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/hello-comet#resource-usage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Resource Usage" title="Direct link to Resource Usage">​</a></h3>
<p>The next concern I had was if the CM3588 was going to have sufficient power. I really wanted to be able to run a fully encapsulated Autonomys Node + Farmer with a 8x COMET cluster, even if one of those was a dedicated Node. To do this I fully plotted two COMETs and created a few different setups. For all these tests I had the maximum cooling (Heatsinks + 50mm Fan)</p>
<p><strong>Farmer Only</strong></p>
<p>For the first test I am using COMET-Alpha as a dedicated Farmer. This is the least amount of resource usage.</p>
<p><strong>Node Only</strong></p>
<p>Next, I wanted to see what sort of stress running a Node on the COMET would provide. In order to get the full picture, I started with a fresh node, storing the Node Data on a USB mounted SSD.</p>
<p><strong>Farmer + Plotter</strong></p>
<p>Moving back to farming, I wanted to see how it would handle running both a Farmer and a Plotter. I never intended to perform initial plotting with these, so the NVMEs are fully plotted. My goal here is to see if these can handle replotting or if I will need to always have a dedicated GPU plotter hooked up to them.</p>
<p><strong>Full Cluster</strong></p>
<p>If I really want to have these self-plot, at least one of them will require a full Cluster which includes a Controller, Cache, and NATs. In this configuration, the COMET is once again fully plotted and will only be handling replots. The Cache is stored on a USB connected SSD and set to 110GiB which should be enough to hold a full cache.</p>
<p><strong>Farming Cluster + Node</strong></p>
<p>Finally, I brought in a second COMET to see how a fully self-reliant COMET cluster would perform. In order to spread the load as efficiently as possible I have the following configuration:</p>
<p>COMET Alpha - Node + Cluster Farmer
COMET Bravo - Cluster Farmer, Cluster Cache, Cluster Controller, Cluster Plotter, NATs</p>
<p>My thought with this is that the Node is extremely resource intensive, so I will put as much of the Cluster components as I can on the other COMET to spread the load.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Comet</category>
            <category>Autonomys</category>
            <category>Linux</category>
            <category>cm3588</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title>
            <link>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://hakehardware.github.io/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I have decided to move all of my guides to Github Pages! This allows me more control over my content and makes it a lot easier to keep guides up to date!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have decided to move all of my guides to Github Pages! This allows me more control over my content and makes it a lot easier to keep guides up to date!</p>
<p>I plan to have quite a bit of content on:</p>
<ol>
<li>General Linux &amp; Windows guides</li>
<li>Blockchains like Autonomys and Spacemesh</li>
<li>COMET</li>
<li>And more!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>